Guide to the Marguerite Johnston Barnes Personal Papers, 1926-2000 MS 491
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Marguerite Johnston Barnes Personal Papers
1926-2000
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Barnes, Marguerite Johnston
MS 491
7.5 Linear Feet (15 boxes)
The bulk of these papers represent Barnes' writing and journalism career, from her early college years to her lengthy career at the Houston Post newspaper. Included are photocopies of her articles, columns, reviews and editorials, typescripts of her works, photographs, and a small amount of family and biographical materials.
Biographical Note
Born in Birmingham, AL, Barnes' early journalistic experience was as assistant editor of her college newspaper at Birmingham-Southern College. She worked on the Birmingham News newspaper as a reporter and as Washington correspondent, and continued as correspondent for the Birmingham Age-Herald and the London Daily Mirror. She was accredited to the Senate and House Press Galleries and White House, and also as United Nations correspondent.
Barnes joined the Houston Post in 1947 as reporter and columnist, and added foreign news editor and assistant editor to her credentials. She served as writing lecturer and instructor for University of Houston and Rice University. She is the recipient of numerous awards from a variety of respected Texas groups, and is well known for her books Public Manners, A Happy Worldly Abode, and Houston, the Unknown City 1836-1936.
Ms. Barnes passed away on December 13, 2005, in Houston, Texas.
Scope and Contents
The Marguerite Johnston Barnes Personal Papers represent Barnes' writing career, from her college years to her career at the Houston Post newspaper and a small amount of biographical family materials, calendars, financial records, and photographs. The bulk of the materials represent her writing career, from her book A Happy Wordly Abode, to her newspaper work for Birmingham, AL newspapers to the Houston Post (later purchased by the Houston Chronicle). Newspaper materials include notes relating ideas for news stories, photocopies of her articles, columns, reviews and editorials, typescripts of her works.
For papers related to Barnes' Houston, The Unknown City, 1830-1991, see Marguerite Johnston Barnes Research Materials for Houston, The Unknown City, 1830-1991, MS 455, Woodson Research Center.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research. Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Acquisition Information
This material was donated by Marguerite Johnton Barnes in 2001-2003.
Related Materials
See also Marguerite Johnston Barnes Research Materials for Houston, The Unknown City, 1830-1991, MS 455, Woodson Research Center.
Index Terms
Subjects
Politics and government; Journalism; Women journalists; Universities and colleges; Women
Document Types
typescripts; clippings (information artifacts); corrrespondence; photographs; calendars; financial records; newspapers
Subjects (Persons)
Barnes, Marguerite Johnston; Barnes, Marguerite Johnston
- Series I: Family Materials, 1946-1998
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials include biographical information on and photographs of Barnes, family ledgers, trip information.
  - Biographical (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photos and visual materials, including digitized version of ca. 1950s 16 mm family film footage, 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Family personal, 1920s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ledger #1, 1956-1961 (R.C. Johnston's finances) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ledger #2, 1961-1966 (R.C. Johnston's finances) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ledger #3, 1967-1973 (R.C. Johnston's finances) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1946-47, 1950, 1953, 1955, 1959, 1960, 1965, 1969-70, 1977, 1979, 1984, 1989-92, 1995, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bonn, Germany visit, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Text for speech on Houston, The Unknown City, Sept. 1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Day books, calendars, 1957, 1960, 1962-63, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Writing, 1931-1998
  Included are materials from the book, A Happy Wordly Abode, Birmingham, AL newspaper articles and columns, The Houston Post articles, reviews, editorials and columns, book collaboration, story/column ideas, proposals, and typescripts.
  - Subseries A: Early school writing
    - Early school writing, 1931, 1936, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Subseries B: A Happy Worldly Abode
    - Research materials (Box 2)
    - Christ Church May Fete, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Visuals (Box 2)
    - Bibliography (Box 2)
    - Partial typescript (Box 2)
    - Partial galley proof (Box 2)
    - Book reviews, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Library of Congress catalog cards, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Subseries C: Birmingham newspapers
    - Articles, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
    - Articles, 1939 (Box 3)
    - Articles, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Articles, 1941 (Box 3)
    - Articles, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Articles, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Articles, 1944 (Box 3)
    - Articles, 1945 (Box 3)
    - Articles, 1946 (Box 3)
    - Articles, undated (1/2) (Box 3)
    - Articles, undated (2/2) (Box 3)
    - About Birmingham," 1940s (1/2) (Box 3)
    - About Birmingham," 1940s (2/2) (Box 3)
    - Weather-related articles, 1940s, n.d. (Box 4)
    - "Ration Diary," 1943-45 (Box 4)
    - Reviews, 1941-44 (Box 4)
  - Subseries D: Houston Post
    - Articles, 1947 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1949 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1950 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1951 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1952 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1955 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1959 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1965 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Articles, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Articles, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Articles, 1980s (Box 5)
    - Articles, 1990s (Box 5)
    - Articles, undated (Box 5)
    - Editorials, 1949-1983, n.d. (1/2) (Box 5)
    - Editorials, 1949-1983, n.d. (2/2) (Box 5)
    - Reviews, 1947-50, 1959-65, 1967-70, 1982, n.d. (Box 5)
    - "Prelude," 1956 (Box 5)
    - "Of Earth and High Winds," 1947-1955 (Box 5)
    - "Not to Change the Subject," 1947 (Box 6)
    - "Not to Change the Subject," 1949 (Box 6)
    - "Not to Change the Subject," 1950 (Box 6)
    - "Not to Change the Subject," 1951 (Box 6)
    - "Not to Change the Subject," 1950s undated (Box 6)
    - "Not to Change the Subject," undated (Box 6)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1951 (Box 7)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1952 (Box 7)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1953 (Box 7)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1954 (Box 7)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1955 (Box 7)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1956 (Box 8)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1957 (Box 8)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1958 (Box 8)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1959 (Box 8)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1960 (Box 8)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1961 (Box 9)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1962 (Box 9)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1963 (Box 9)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1964 Jan.-June (Box 9)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1964 Sept.-Dec. (Box 9)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1965 (Box 9)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1966 (Box 9)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1967 (Box 9)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1968 (Box 9)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1952-1953 undated (Box 10)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1953-1954 undated (Box 10)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1954-1955 undated (Box 10)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1955-1956 undated (Box 10)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1956-1957 undated (Box 10)
    - "Marguerite Johnston," 1957-1964 undated (Box 10)
    - Other newspaper articles, 1940s-1960s, 1998 (Box 10)
    - Instruction for Your Baby (collaboration with Dr. Laura Bickel), n.d. (Box 10)
    - Public Manners, n.d. (Box 10)
    - Ideas for columns (Box 10)
    - Dior article notes Typescript proposal for sesquicentennial history of Houston, 1984 (Box 10)
    - Typescript for future Houston airport, 1968 (Box 10)
    - Typescripts for articles and columns (Box 11)
    - United Nations materials, 1946, 1948 (Box 11)
- Series III: Photographs, 1963-1970, n.d.
  Included are photos for related stories (mostly travel-related).
  - Denmark, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Dusseldorf (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Finland, Sweden (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Italy, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Japan and Bangkok, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Mexico (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Norway, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Round Top, TX, 1963, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous photos (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Awards, 1956-1997
  - Houston Committee on Alcoholism, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Houston Teachers Association, 1970, 1974, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - American Society of Safety Engineers, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Houston Sportsmen's Club, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Alief/Southwest Houston Chamber of Commerce, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - National Council on Alcoholism, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Yates Senior High School, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Houston Professional Firefighters Association, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Birmingham-Southern College, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Texas Society of Architects, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Garden Club of Houston, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Population Action Council, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - East Texas Historical Association, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Texas School Bell, 1973, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Citizens' Environmental Coalition, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Texas Corrections Association, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - YWCA, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Daughters of the Republic of Texas, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - San Jacinto Senior High School, 1997 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Newsclips (Box 12, Folder 20)
- Series V: Notes and correspondence, 1977-2000
  - Notes of interview with Michael DeBakey, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified handwritten notes (Box 13, Folder 2-6)
  - Notes for talks (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Daybook, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Appointment book and notes, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Appointment book and notes, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Appointment book and notes, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Appointment book, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Appointment book, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Daybook, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Planner and notes, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Address books (Box 14, Folder 9-10)
  - Contacts, Africa (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Notes (handwritten) (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Reporter's notebook (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Notebook: McAshan interview, Spring 1984 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Malcolm Lovett interview audiotape, 1984-05-29 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Slide: Photo of Marguerite Johnston, 1984-03 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Photocopy: 1876 Opera House Tableaux and Ball (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Expense Ledger, 1984-1990 (Box 14, Folder 18-19)
  - Correspondence, 1964-2000 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Information on Christ Church (A Happy Worldly Abode) (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Information on Glenwood Cemetery (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Proposal for "Houston: The Unknown City" (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
  - Notebook: Trip to France (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - "A Day Visit to Knappague Castle in County Clare, Ireland" by Mark Edwin Andrews (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - "Lawrenceville School" and "Happy memories from Six Decades Long Ago" by Mark Edwin Andrews (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Town & Country Magazine (on Houston), 1991-09 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - 'Southern: A Publication for Alumni and Friends of Birmingham-Southern College - (article re: Marguerite Johnston Barnes), 2006 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Articles (copies): Sisterdale, San Antonio March 4, 1934; National Gazette May 10, 1836 (Box 15, Folder 11)